# Ethan J. Shang

Cell: (925) 321-9181 email: ethanshang@berkeley.edu website: ethanjshang.github.io U.S. Citizen

**Profile:** Full-stack developer of user-facing applications with experience in database query design, network security, data visualizations and analytics, and machine learning with an interest in product management.

#### Education

University of California, Berkeley, Class of 2020 (Junior), GPA: 3.55, Computer Science GPA: 3.65

o Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

o Regents' and Chancellor's Scholar

Granada High School, Class of 2017; GPA: 4.52 (4.0 unweighted)

Las Positas Community College, GPA: 4.0 (2016–2017, concurrent enrollment during high school)

Sandia National Laboratories Cyber Technology Academy (2014–2015)

# **Employment and Work Experience**

Software Engineering Intern, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory (2018)

 Project: Data analytic tool to improve supercomputer performance—automate analysis by integrating disparate data; created query language and parser for language-agnostic queries via web-based dashboard

# Research Assistant, UC Berkeley RISELab (Real-Time Intelligence with Secure Execution) (2018)

- o RISELab (NSF Expedition Lab): To improve machines' decision-making based on real-time input
- o **Project**: To streamline the integration of machine-learning techniques into user-facing applications

Academic Intern, University of California, Berkeley (2017–2018)

o Official course staff — Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

Computer Security Intern, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory (2016–2017)

- o **Project (2017)**: Data mining and assessment of the Department of Energy's vast network to improve threat detection; Leadership role in developing autonomous analytical software from the ground up
- Project (2016): Created tools to monitor network data from mobile devices by parsing packets; correlated
  physical movement with network data to provide security assessment and improve workplace efficiency

#### Skills and Abilities

- o Programming languages: Java, C++, Python, Scala, Bash, SQL, Scheme
- o Tools: Git, Jupyter Notebook, Microsoft Office Suite
- o Information Management: database query design, user-defined libraries, API design
- o Big Data: automation, aggregation, data-mining, and resource-management applications
- o Machine learning: leveraging Yelp's Open Dataset to predict and visualize user preferences
- o Network Security: Packet/protocol analysis, data mining, encryption, cryptography, wireless penetration
- Coursework: Data Structures, Computer Architecture, Designing Information Devices and Systems,
   Discrete Math and Probability, Electricity and Magnetism, Multivariate Calculus, Efficient Algorithms and
   Intractable Problems (upcoming), Machine Learning, iOS Design/Development, Ethics/Law in Cybersecurity

# Leadership Experience

## Youth Commissioner, Livermore Area Youth Advisory Commission (2015–2017)

- Leadership role on citywide commission to help youths in underserved demographics with academic pursuits
   Technical Lead, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory (2017)
- o Managed development of analytics tool collaboratively, interfaced with team members of diverse disciplines

## **Notable Awards**

- o UC Berkeley Regents' and Chancellor's Scholarship Top 3% of Berkeley students
- o National Merit Scholarship Finalist <1% of U.S. high school seniors
- o California Legislature Assembly Certificate of Recognition, 2017
- National Certificate of Merit in Piano, Level 10; Fusion Soccer Athlete-Scholar of the Year
- o Recipient of seven merit-based scholarships in science and engineering